<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <body>
        <h1>Welcome to WSO2 Data Services Server, 3.1.1</h1>

        <h2>26 Aug 2013 - WSO2 Data Services Server, 3.1.1 Released!</h2>

        <p>[<a
                href="http://wso2.com/products/data-services-server/">Download</a>]
            | [<a href="index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>] | [<a
                    href="release_notes.html">Release Note</a>]
        </p>

        <p>The WSO2 Data Services Server is an extremely simple and elegant mechanism to take data
            and make it available as a set of WS-* style Web services or as a set of REST style Web
            resources. It augments SOA development efforts by providing an easy to use platform for
            creating and hosting data services. This enables easy integration of data into business
            processes, mashups, gadgets, BI applications and any service in general.
        </p>

        <p><img src="images/ds_archi.png"/>
                <br/>
                Figure : Architecture view of WSO2 Data Services Server.
       </p>

        <p>The WSO2 Data Services Server is built on top of the WSO2 Carbon platform. It utilizes
            many features made available by the Carbon platform. A data service can be summarized
            into a XML descriptor file written in compliance with Data Services Descriptor Language
            (DSDL). DSDL is a XML based language defined by WSO2 to write data services.
        </p>

        <p>A custom deployer, written extending the Apache Axis2 deployer framework is responsible
            for reading this data service descriptor and creating a data service. High performant
            XML processing capabilities offered by Apache AXIOM is used for generating XML responses
            on the fly. Some of the third party open source projects used by the WSO2 Data Services
            Server includes Apache DBCP for managing connection pools for Relational Databases,
            Google Spreadsheet Data API for reading Google Spreadsheets, OpenCSV for CSV file
            support and Apache POI for MS-Excel support.
        </p>
        <h2>WSO2 Data Services Server, Documentation</h2>

        <p>See the
            <a href="index_docs.html">full list of documents</a>
            with
            instructions on installation, administration, sample guides and how to use
            the tools packaged with WSO2 Data Services Server , 3.1.1 .
        </p>
        <a></a>

        <h2>Mailing Lists</h2>

        <p>Your feedback on WSO2 Data Services Server is most appreciated. Please send them to our
            user mailing lists:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>WSO2 Data Services Server, Users' mailing list:
                <a
                        href="mailto:user@wso2.org">user@wso2.org
                </a>                
            </li>
        </ul>
        <ul>
            <li>WSO2 Data Services Server, Developers' mailing list
                <a
                        href="mailto:dev@wso2.org">dev@wso2.org
                </a>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <h3></h3>

    </body>
</html>
